hello and welcome to a brand new episode
of smart money on today's episode we do
a deep dive on how you can select the
right health insurance plan what are the
things you need to evaluate before
picking your health insurance and we'll
also help you with an age-wise breakdown
on how much Insurance you need at what
age what are the premiums you need to
pay for it as well joining us on the
show is Girish nyak he's a chief
technology health and officer at ICI
Lombard Gish thanks a lot for joining us
on NBC TV8 uh well you know I want to
first start with what the importance of
health insurance is in today's economy
because a lot of young people a lot of
people reach out to me saying we just
don't know how to start our insurance
Journey so uh what is your advice to
them thank you Sonia for having me on
the show and uh like you said it's a
very important uh topic because uh not
many people are really aware of health
insurance uh and it's a very important
aspect of financial planning uh health
insurance costs uh the healthcare costs
are rising and the medical costs are
really rising and uh almost every year
we have 63 million Indians who actually
fall below poverty line uh because of
healthcare uh costs and that's a huge
number so uh planning for a financial
emergency is extremely important and
health insurance helps you to do that
now there are many kinds of health
insurance two main kinds are basically
uh the group insurance and the
individual insurance most of us are
familiar with the group insurance
policies which uh you have with your
employer the employer will have a group
insurance policy and uh all the
employees are typically covered by it
there's also the individual insurance
policies where you can take it as a
individual and there are many kinds of
uh individual insurance policies that
you have but I think what is more
important that every individual should
have some sort of health insurance
policy to protect against unforeseen
medical uh emergencies sure that's very
important I want to talk a little bit
about that right because all of us
employees have a corporate policy but
you spoke about the different types of
health insurance there's group health
insurance there is individual health
insurance so for someone who already has
corporate Insurance do you need to take
a top up do you also need an individual
health insurance can you just explain a
little more sure see if Group insurance
policies typically will cover all
employees in a group and uh the cover is
generally around four to 5 lakhs
uh per individual some employes also
offer uh coverage to maybe spouse spouse
children if the employers are very
generous spouse children parents so
there are different kinds of cover that
uh employers provide but most of these
covers are typically about four to 5
lakhs and that really doesn't suffice
for a family uh health insurance uh
cover so it is always advisable to have
an individual insurance cover as well
now normally uh also what happens is
when you are in employ employment you
typically don't worry about this thing
saying that your kind of employes is
going to cover you and you would be on
until retirement but when you retire say
at the age of 60 and suddenly you
realize you are without a cover at that
point in time going and getting cover
will be very expensive unless you had a
cover from a significantly earlier age
so that's one reason why you should get
a health insurance cover even though you
have a group Insurance Group cover that
is covering you the other U other thing
is that uh the uh coverage of the group
insurance policy is typically limited to
what the employer kind of uh decides for
you here you as individual you can kind
of uh have a lot more add-ons that you
want which are more suited to your
requirements and hence uh having an
individual insurance policy is always
better than just having only the group
insurance cover that you normally go
with okay so we talking about the
advantages of personal uh retail
insurance right so individual insurance
basically uh you spoke about how you get
to decide what the cover can be as
opposed to your you know employer
deciding and the other thing is when you
retire you will not just be left without
an insurance so always better to have an
individual not only when you retire say
for example you quit your job quit your
job and want to become an entrepreneur
yes at that point in time again you you
might be wanting to set out on the
exciting Journey but it's better if you
have a individual cover at that point in
time okay so you at least the any
Healthcare emergency is covered so when
you're seeing a corporate insurance you
have that you do a top up or you take a
separate individual insurance insurance
policy again there there are multiple
options that you you can take uh a
separate individual insurance policy is
always best because it covers you right
from the base so tomorrow like for
example I said if you go out of the
corporate job and you want to start off
on your own you have a cover right from
Bas but yes some people from point of
view of their budget would want to take
a topup uh policy so top-ups are much
cheaper than the uh taking a full cover
so if you want to take uh a cover for
say 15 lakhs and your uh employer is
giving you uh 3 lakh cover you say take
a topup which will cover you from 3
lakhs to 15 lakhs so that'll be cheaper
than taking a full 15 lakh cover but at
the same time you should realize that
when your Group Insurance stops the
first three lakhs will still be need to
be covered by you so you need that base
cover at some point in time so again
it's advisable to take a individual uh
complete insurance policy and just a
topup uh if you can afford it okay I
want to talk about starting insurance at
a younger age right what are the
benefits of buying health insurance at a
younger age and what age is the right
age to
start good question I mean uh it's
always good to start early uh again from
a health insurance point of view uh the
healthier the life the lower the
insurance younger uh customers always
have a lower Insurance uh premium and
given our lifestyles today and the kind
of uh stress that is there uh invariably
you see people over 40 45 ending up
having some kind of a lifestyle uh
whether it's hypertension blood the
diabetes India is the diabetes capital
of the world so once you have any of
these when you get into a insurance
policy at that point in time these get
marked off as pre-existing diseases and
your cover the premium is always higher
but if you're already on a policy and
you contract that's there your premium
would not change because there you
didn't have those uh conditions when you
contracted the policy so it's always
better to get in at early age um when
you start your career start off with
insurance policy okay I want to
understand is health insurance a tax
saving tool or should you look at it
separately well there there is advantage
of tax saving as well because uh uh you
have up to age of 60 years you can cover
yourself and your family and under
Section 80d you get a cover of up to
25,000 of a premium you can set off uh
if you're covering a parents uh who are
above 60 then you get additional 50,000
uh set off under the U section 80d so
that okay but you shouldn't look at it
as a tax saving tool right that's an
added benefit it's an added benefit it's
added benefit so you when you want to do
your financial calculations it does help
saying that okay this much is coming
back to me as a tax saving but I would
look at it purely as a protection which
you need because one is makinging
Investments to grow your Capital but
there kind of protection for your
capital in case there is any emergency
you don't draw from your Capital to pay
for it so you have something which takes
care of that uh absolutely absolutely so
I do want to know how much health
insurance do I need age wise right but
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
take a short commercial break don't go
anywhere when we come back we'll tell
you how to plan your health insurance to
secure your future in just a
bit